So בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Start today on דף נז, Daf Nun
Zayin, top of the דף, daf, two lines from the top.
And we are going through the problems that might occur by birds
which do not make it a טריפה. tereifah. So we had already
the guts falling out but still attached, but the stomach had broken
open. And now we go to some more minor problems. נשברו רגליה,
Nishbaru ragleha, if its leg had broken, and then it says or
the wings had broken and so on. So let's take a look.
ההוא צנא דאינקורי, Hahu tsana de'inkurei, there was a basket of birds.
Now צנא tsana normally means something like a basket, but what are
אינקורי inkurei exactly? So there's an interesting רש״י Rashi who says it
might refer to a particular type of bird. If you look at
the last line of the wide lines of רש״י Rashi in the
middle sort of there, he says: ובתשובת הגאונים מצאתי, Uve-tshuvat ha-Geonim matsati,
I found in the responsa of הגאונים, ha-Geonim, עוף שחור הוא, of
shakhor hu, a black bird, ושל מים הוא, veshel mayim hu, a
waterfowl, ובמצחו חברברות לבנות, uve-mitskho khavarbarot levanot,
with white splotches on its forehead. Anybody know what type of black
waterfowl that might be? And then he says ועל שם כך נקראו
אינקורי שהוא מנומר כמו ניקובי פינטורא, ve-al shem kakh nikru inkurei shehu
menumar kemo nikuvei pintura,
so he says that the word אינקורי inkurei means like it has
splotches, it has dots or spots. And then he says ובעיר הזאת
יש מהם, u-ve-ir ha-zot yesh mehem, in this city where רש״י Rashi
was living in France, he says we have these types of birds,
black waterfowl with white splotches on their heads. So I don't know
what they are but that's what the תשובת הגאונים... Teshuvat ha-Geonim... I
thought it was funny that he says ובעיר הזאת, u-ve-ir ha-zot, like
very specific.
The ArtScroll says
a harlequin duck.
Harlequin duck.
Well, maybe that's that.
That would follow רש״י's Rashi's description.
It says רש״י Rashi explains the name which literally means
punctured reflects the fact that the white spots against the black background
appear like punctures.
Okay, very nice. Harlequin duck. Okay. So anyway, so we had this
basket of birds or of ducks, דאתא לקמיה דרבא, de-ata lekamei de-Rava,
came to רבא. Rava. בדקי רבא בצומת הגידין. Badke Rava bi-tsomet ha-gidim.
Now apparently there were some broken leg bones which fits in with
our discussion. Leg, leg,
now by animals by the way they make a distinction between the
forearms or forelegs and the rear legs. Birds only have like the
two feet, the two legs. But okay, so in mammals, in cows
or whatever, interestingly though not really mentioned in any of our משניות
mishnayot which go to these extensive lists, but alluded to or whatever,
referred to a few times in the גמרא Gemara and will come
a focus in the next פרק, perek, is a טריפה tereifah called
the broken foreleg, hind leg, excuse me, the broken hind leg.
And it speaks about if the bone breaks מן הארכובה ולמעלה, min
ha-arkuva u-lemala, from the knee and above. Now the thing with animals
is that they actually have or cows two knees, right? If you
take a look at this picture I don't know if you can
see it well enough here, but you see there's like a hinge
over here and then another hinge over here, right? So this is
sort of closer to our heel but it actually is somewhat like
hinged. I mean anyway. So ארכובה arkuva there's some discussion but the
general assumption is that ארכובה arkuva means this lower knee, right, like
ממש mamash right near the heel, okay, the or the ankle I
guess I'd say, the ankle. Okay. So it says that if the
animal that bone broke from this ankle or above it's a טריפה,
tereifah, which would seem surprising, right, because like it does not seem
like it's a major injury, it hasn't been listed on any of
our lists. Nevertheless, that's what the, there's going to, the גמרא's Gemara's
going to say, the משנה's mishna's going to say in a משנה
mishna in the next פרק. perek. Again interesting that it's absent from
this דף daf although it's been referred to. Now there's also something
called the צומת הגידין, tsomet ha-gidim, the like cluster of like sinews,
which occurs at, at this position where the משנה mishna also says
that if that cluster has somehow been severed or removed or whatever,
even if the bone has not broken, it's also a טריפה. tereifah.
So you have those two טריפות tereifot by cows and I guess
sheep and whatever and goats: the break at the lower ankle and
the, and the removal or the cutting of the cluster of the
sinews. Let me just see quickly if there's some picture of that
from the later גמרא. Gemara. Well they have a picture by the
bird ובצומת... u-ve-tsomet... no hold on.
They probably have a better picture I would imagine in the what
do you call it? They probably have a better picture in
the שיחת חולין. Sikhat Chullin. Anyway, so here, okay, so look, but
this actually isn't bad. Okay. So here's your cow, alright, so actually,
I don't know how well you can see this, here's your cow,
over here like literally like into the actual animal itself, this is
where you know, this is where the top... sort of leg is
hinged. Okay. Down here is where there's a lower hinge. So the
צומת הגידים Tzomet Hagidim is this cluster here of various sinews and
muscles or whatever right here around this part of the leg. Okay.
Let's see what it says here. The middle section, blah blah blah,
צומת הגידים, Tzomet Hagidim, meeting of the sinews along the back of
the leg, okay. Anyway fine. So that's what's the problem by cows,
okay, and other large animals. We will talk about it more when
we get to it. So now it says like this. And now
the question is, so number one, it's sort of surprising that it's
not at all in this פרק. Perek. It appears in the fourth
פרק Perek and discusses cows. Now the question is also does that
logically apply to birds? Because we said whatever טרפות Treifot we have
by cows applies to birds and if it does, so if there's
a טריפה Treifah about the breaking of a hind leg of a
cow at an even at a very low place in that leg,
so a broken leg of a bird should be a problem. Of
course a bird doesn't have forearms or hind legs, so maybe it's
not easy to do the equation, but if we want to apply
one to the next, so let's take a look. So here we
have רבא Rava who is checking this cluster of sinews in the
leg of a bird to see that it has not been severed.
Okay. ואכשריה Ve'achshereih and he says oh okay it hasn't been severed
it's כשר. Kosher. Which means that if it had been severed it
would be a problem even in a bird. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said
in the name of רב Rav thank you very much for bringing
me my coffee this morning. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav שמוטת יד בבהמה כשירה Shmutat yad bivehemah kesherah שמוטת
ירך בבהמה טריפה. Shmutat yerech bivehemah tereifah.
Now let's say you're not talking about a broken leg or severed
sinews, you're talking about dislocated. So a dislocated forearm of a בהמה
Behemah is כשירה, Kesherah, with the parentheses in the back, a dislocated
hind leg is a טריפה. Tereifah. You might have remembered we actually
mentioned that earlier. That was one of the שבע שמעתתא Sheva Shmaytata
which was
something דשף מדוכתיה. Deshaf miduchteih. What's it called again?
אטמא? Atma? Oh yeah, בוקא דאטמא דשף מדוכתיה, Buka de'atma deshaf miduchteih,
the hind thigh that was dislocated from the hip bone. Okay, so
dislocated rear leg of a בהמה Behemah is a טריפה. Tereifah. שמוטת
ירך בעוף טריפה. Shmutat yerech be'of tereifah. So by analogy a dislocated
thigh of a bird is also a טריפה. Tereifah. Okay now again
it's presumably we're talking about these legs. I don't know if a
bird has how it looks like by a bird, I don't know
if you have a picture, here's a picture. So does it have
I don't know why does it have front and back? It doesn't
have front and back.
The wing could be the wing is like an arm, a ירך.
Yerech.
Bird wings are equivalent to forearms
right but forearms right and this is feeding the bird's legs like
the hind leg
so they and that okay.
So this is interesting. So thank you this is a good picture.
So here the thigh bone right by an animal it would be
the thigh bone where it connects to the hip. Here by the
bird look how look how high the thigh bone is connected. It's
connected like to the almost the spinal cord right? I guess that's
true you know if you think about it our hip is the
bottom of our spinal cord. Okay so if it's dislocated by a
bird so basically what we've done the upshot of these two teachings
is we have assumed as Charlie correctly pointed out and I didn't
think about it that the wings were like the forelegs. So we've
assumed that the feet of the bird are like the hind legs
and we've applied two טרפות Treifot that we know by בהמה. Behemah.
One טריפה Treifah is a severing of this collection of the sinews,
the צומת הגידים, Tzomet Hagidim, which we haven't even seen yet. And
the other is the dislocated thigh bone okay which was one of
the שבע שמעתתא. Sheva Shmaytata. So now we've applied this to birds.
שמוטת גף בעוף טריפה. Shmutat gaff be'of tereifah. Now a dislocated wing
is a טריפה. Tereifah. Now that's unusual because that should be like
a dislocated forearm. Why is that a טריפה? Tereifah? So we're about
to see not intrinsically but because of a problem it might have
created. חיישינן שמא ניקבה הריאה. Chayshinan shema nikvah hareiah.
We're afraid that in the process of dislocating the wing, right think
the wing is located like roughly where the arm is or whatever
right it could have caused a puncture in the lung. So that's
not an intrinsic problem but we're afraid of what might have come
about. Yes.
But the משנה Mishnah didn't mention the lungs at first.
Oh the משנה Mishnah didn't mention a lot of things. We first
have a statement which is which you know anything that's true by
בהמה Behemah is true by a bird unless you know otherwise which
is completely absent right from the משנה Mishnah which it enormously extends
the list. And now we're taking things that we haven't even really
mentioned explicitly yet by בהמות Behemot which were these hind leg problems
and we're also applying it to birds. So you're correct. But if
you know once you buy into all of those additional assumptions this
is what comes out. The גמרא Gemara will actually challenge some of
this by bird for the remainder of the דף. Daf. Yes.
Birds can live indefinitely with injured wings.
Well that's what the משנה Mishnah says. A broken wing is not
a problem. So that's why it didn't say broken wing, it said
dislocated where it connects to the you know to the actual whatever
it connects to structure and that might cause a puncture. Now if
it's only a concern it might cause a puncture you could disagree
with that concern, you could test for it, you could check for
it. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Okay.
And שמואל אמר Shmuel amar so שמואל Shmuel says תיבדק. tivdeik. No,
if it's a dislocated wing and you're concerned about the lung, check
the lung. Don't say it's a טריפה. treifa. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן
V'chen amar Rebbe Yochanan תיבדק tivdeik and רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says
check it. חזקיה אמר Chizkiya amar חזקיה Chizkiya said אין ריאה לעוף,
ein reia l'of, birds don't have lungs. So
one minute, the גמרא Gemara is going to have an interesting discussion
about that. ורבי יוחנן אמר V'Rebbe Yochanan amar רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan
said יש לו, yesh lo, no birds have lungs. וישנה כעלה של
ורד, V'yeshna k'aleh shel vered, it's very small, it looks like the
leaf of a rose. Okay? So do they have a picture of
it? They do. It doesn't look so tiny, but that's a big
bird.
Okay, it's a chicken. All right.
It's a chicken has lungs.
Yeah, obviously, obviously it has lungs. Okay so it says it is,
but it's like a so anyway it's small, it looks like a
little leaf, but it has a lung. So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to say, okay, בין אגפיים bein agapayim and that's located
between the wings. Okay, so now we're going to obviously try to
understand so you can understand the question about is it a טריפה
treifa do you just check, you know, or can you check for
it? But what is this issue that it doesn't have lungs? Now
by the way, notice that our משנה, Mishna, when it as Charlie
said, when it mentioned the טריפה treifa of birds, did not mention
lungs. So that somebody would come and say that it doesn't have
lungs if it's not mentioned in the משנה, Mishna, I mean if
maybe all you have is text and not actual birds, you might
come with that conclusion. Or okay, but so let's take a look.
Where were we?
Okay, מאי אין ריאה לעוף? mai ein reia l'of? What does חזקיה
Chizkiya mean when he says there are no lungs to a bird?
אילימא דלית ליה כלל, ileima d'leis lei klal, if he literally means
there are no lungs, והא חזינא דאית ליה, ve'ha qhazina d'is lei,
we see that there are lungs. Anybody who's ever cut up a
chicken and looked at it can see the lung. Okay, אלא דלא
מיטרפי, ela d'lo mitreifei, maybe it just means halachically I don't care
about the lung, which again is possible given that the משנה Mishna
doesn't mention it. But one minute, הא תני לוי, ha tanyei Levi,
לוי Levi taught and this is the one that fills in all
of the not mentioned things in the משנה Mishna by birds, טריפה
שמנו חכמים בבהמה, treifa she'manu chachamim b'vehema, all of the טריפות treifas
that are listed by large animals, by mammals, כנגדן בעוף k'negdan b'of
apply to a bird, יתר להן בעוף yeter lahen b'of and a
bird even has more than a mammal. Which are they? נשבר העצם
אף על פי שלא ניקב קרום של מוח, nishbar ha'etzem af al
pi she'lo nikav krum she'al moach, what we taught yesterday, if the
skull of the head cracked open even if there's not a hole
in the membrane, which we said was about waterfowl. But anyway we
have this statement which says that you apply all of the טריפות.
treifas. Okay, so how he can't mean just straight there's no problem
with lungs because we know we would apply the טריפה. treifa. So
what does he mean there's no lung? אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi
ka'amar, he must mean, אין לו לא לינפול ולא ליחמר. ein lo
lo linpol v'lo l'chamer.
So we're still trying to have him admit that there are lungs,
but it means maybe we don't have to worry about the lungs
in two cases. What are the two cases? When the animal falls
לינפול linpol from the roof, right? And we say that you have
to check the inner organs. So there was a question, you know,
wait 24 hours and you check the inner organs. Which inner organs
do you check? Just the gastrointestinal ones or all of the inner
organs? So maybe he says, oh, you don't have to worry about
checking the lung by a bird, maybe it's well protected by the
rib cage. And or when it falls into a fire and we
say has they turned red or not, did they change color? Maybe
there you would say you don't have to worry about the lungs,
they're protected. So maybe just means the lungs are protected in those
two scenarios, when it fell לינפול, linpol, where is it, or ליחמר,
l'chamer, מחמר machmer
is the word for like the shriveling of the organ as a
result of the fire. So that you don't have to worry. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? אמר רב
חנא amar Rav Chana הואיל ורוב צלעותיה מגינות עליה ho'il v'rov tzaloteha
m'ginot aleha because its ribs protect it. And רש"י Rashi actually points
out that actually the ribs create like a dome, so it's not
just like they're a physical barrier but they're actually like, you know,
there's a space, they create actually like a gap between where the
ribs are and then where those organs are. So maybe that's what
he means, that if some trauma occurs you don't have to assume
that the lungs were damaged. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
say, one minute, והא מדאמר רבי יוחנן יש לו וישנה כעלה של
ורד בין אגפיים? v'ha mid'amar Rebbe Yochanan yesh lo v'yeshna k'aleh shel
vered bein agapayim? Since רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan responds to חזקיה Chizkiya
by saying it does have a lung and it looks like a
little leaf and it's right between, you know, the wings. So it's
pretty clear what חזקיה Chizkiya was saying,
right? מכלל דחזקיה סבר דלית ליה. miklal d'Chizkiya savar d'leis lei. It
sounds like חזקיה Chizkiya really thought that a bird doesn't have lungs.
אלא אמרי במערבא, ela amri b'ma'arava, you know what, you're right, and
they say in the West, משמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא mishmei d'Rebbe
Yose b'Rebbe Chanina in the name of רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Rebbe
Yose b'Rebbe Chanina, מדבריו של רבי midivrei shel Rebbe from the words
of the great רבי, Rebbe, so they're sort of respecting him because
they're about to actually have a little fun at his expense, from
the words of this great רבי, Rebbe, ניכר שאינו בקי בתרנגולי, nikar
she'eino baki b'tarnigolei, it's clear that he doesn't know his way around
chickens. Okay, so this is actually quite fascinating. Now on the one
hand you could say, so how is the גמרא Gemara dealing with
you know fifteen דפים dapim of טריפות? treifas? But the point is,
but no, they like basically responded to the one person who tried
to participate in the conversation and didn't know what he was talking
about by saying you don't know what you're talking about then like,
so. Right. Now, even though he's given opinions even though they're ignorant
of the facts, maybe this is a
lesson that
we're
supposed to ignore those ignorant opinions.
Right.
But I could assume one of two things: either he could have
been looking at the משניות, Mishnayot, like I told you, you have
this long list of all the organs by the cows, you don't
have them all listed by the birds. Lungs aren't mentioned by the
birds, so he maybe just was, you know, book smart. Exactly. Just,
you never looked at a chicken, but you just said, look, it
sounds like there's no lungs to birds. The other thing is if
you don't know what you're looking at, right, the fact that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say, no, no, no, it looks like a
leaf and this is where it's located, if you don't know what
you're looking for, if you're used to looking at like these, you
know, big things by a cow and you don't see anything that
looks just like that, you know, when the first time you ever
do dissection, right, you know, somebody has to point out to you
this is what this is and this is what that is. So
it could be he looked at a chicken, he was just oblivious
to, you know, he said, no, I looked, I didn't see any
lungs. So somebody said, you didn't know what you were looking for,
these are what the lungs are. So it is quite fascinating, but
again, I don't see this, it's a good question why he, you
know, rendered an opinion if he was not sufficiently trained in this.
But on the other hand, you know, I take heart from, excuse
all the puns, from the fact that the גמרא, Gemara, you know,
very quickly rejected it and, you know, and, you know, said we,
you know, we do have, we do know what it looks like,
they sort of pointed out that his opinion was not worth being,
you know, sort of considered and so on. So you know, so
but yeah, it is fascinating that he still rendered his opinion. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, I guess what's even
more fascinating is that it was remembered, maybe the גמרא Gemara assumes
that somebody else might make the same mistake so it wanted to
actually record it, right? Why would you even record such an opinion?
All right,
so that was a fascinating digression from the concern about the dislocated
wings. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רב הונא אמר רב:
Amar Rav Huna amar Rav: שמוטת ירך בעוף כשרה. Shamotes yerech be'of
keshera. Where we are back to not the wings, which are just
by analogy to a בהמה, behema, the wings are not a problem,
but there is a concern that they punctured the lungs, and now
we are back to the legs which by analogy to a בהמה
behema is a problem. So we had said that a dislocated leg
by a בהמה behema of a rear leg is a טריפה, treifa,
and now we are saying that a dislocated also thigh bone from
a leg bone of a chicken is a טריפה. treifa. But we
have a different teaching now, and the teaching now is רב הונא
Rav Huna in the name of רב: Rav: שמוטת ירך בעוף כשרה,
Shamotes yerech be'of keshera, that it doesn't follow the rule of a
בהמה. behema. By a בהמה behema that would be a טריפה, treifa,
by a bird it is כשרה. keshera. And this is now what
the גמרא Gemara is going to analyze: are birds in this regard
like בהמות behemot or not? אמר ליה רבא בר בר רב הונא
לרב הונא. Amar lei Raba bar bar Rav Huna le-Rav Huna. So
רבא, Raba, the son of רב הונא, Rav Huna, said to רב
הונא, Rav Huna, said to his father who taught over this in
the name of רב Rav that it wasn't a problem, והרבנן דאתו
מפומבדיתא, ve-ha-rabbanan de-atu mi-Pumbedita,
but the rabbis that came from פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, אמרו amru רב יהודה
משמיה דרב, Rav Yehuda mishmeih de-Rav, had another teaching in the name
of רב, Rav, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of רב,
Rav, you dad are saying this in the name of רב Rav
but there's others who say in the name of רב, Rav, אמר
שמוטת ירך בעוף טריפה, amar shamotes yerech be'of treifa, that a dislocated
thigh bone in a bird makes it a טריפה. treifa. So there's
a different tradition in the name of רב. Rav. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, so רב הונא Rav Huna said back to him, ברי,
beri, my son, נהרא נהרא ופשטיה, nahara nahara u-pashtei, every river and
where it spreads out, like in its tributary. Now what does that
mean? That normally is a phrase, actually we had this came up
a while ago in the גמרא Gemara if you look י"ח עמוד
ב' Yud Chet Amud Bet a good month ago or more, forty
days ago, where it actually was used in the more classic way
which means different places have different practices. There are debates, some places
follow one opinion, some places follow another opinion, we should be tolerant,
you know, of the different practices. It's sort of halakhic pluralism. You
know, every place has its מנהגים minhagim or its different פסקים psakim
but they all follow legitimate authorities and so on. The problem here
is he wasn't just saying there are people who פסקן pasken otherwise,
he was actually saying there's a different tradition in the name of
רב. Rav. So to say every place has its, you know, traditions
is actually, but one is accurate and one isn't accurate. It's not
just like, you know, they follow different authorities, they're actual different traditions
in the name of רב. Rav. So רש"י Rashi says here, if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, נהרא נהרא ופשטיה, nahara nahara u-pashtei, it's
about fifteen lines before the lines get wide, אין פשוטיו של נהר,
ein pishotei ha-nahar, the lines start to twist now, דומין זה לזה.
domin zeh la-zeh. The way the river sort of spreads out, you
know, where
one tributary is not like another, זה חריף וזה עומד, zeh charif
ve-zeh omed, one is rushing water at one point, another point standing
water. כך אין מנהג המקומות דומות, kach ein minhag ha-mekomot domot, the
practices of places are not the same.
ורב, Ve-Rav, now how do you, okay, but these are different traditions
in the name of רב. Rav. So it says, so here's how
רש"י Rashi tries to reconcile. ורב כשרה סבירא ליה, ve-Rav keshera sevira
lei, רב Rav must have really held it's kosher, says רב הונא,
Rav Huna, like my tradition in רב's Rav name.
בתר בני פומבדיתא שנהגו בו איסור, bassar bnei Pumbedita she-nahagu bo issur,
those in פומבדיתא Pumbedita they had a custom to treat it as
a and he didn't want to override their custom. So the way
רש"י, Rashi, you know, explains, how does this answer different reports in
רב's Rav name, and normally this is used for different practices and
different customs. רש"י Rashi says, tries to reconcile it this way. רב
Rav must have really ruled that it was permissible. The fact that
there's other traditions in the name of רב Rav that it was
forbidden, that was when he tolerated places that had that custom, which
he chose not to override due to respect for the customs of
other places. So that's how רש"י Rashi sort of explains it, it
is about sort of respecting other customs and reconciling that רב Rav
really is not contradicting himself. Yes, Charlie.
Another possibility is maybe רב Rav פסק pasken'd differently
in different times.
Right, but then why would you use נהרא נהרא ופשטיה? nahara nahara
u'fastei? You know, you would've said that's what he said earlier, then
he reversed, unless you want to say he פסק pasken'd differently in
different places still retaining his early, his earlier rulings. Maybe. It is
a funny use of this phrase, we must admit.
It's not a custom, you're talking about a הלכה halacha on פסח.
Pesach.
Right, so custom actually is a bad word. You're right, custom is
a bad word, and you know, often מנהג minhag is translated as
custom, but it really at least half of the time means practice.
Means, you know, so חיים סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soloveitchik once said, I don't
know if this was his own sort of, you know, choice of
words or this is more of modern Hebrew, he said we should
distinguish between נהוג nihug and מנהג. minhag. Right, נהוג nihug means, you
know, adopted practice. מנהג minhag means it's a custom, it's not law.
So most of the time, you know, what we really mean here
is נהוג, nihug, not מנהג. minhag. So נהרא נהרא ופשטיה, nahara nahara
u'fastei, right, doesn't just mean you respect customs, although רש"י Rashi here
did use it as a custom, he said really it's permissible but
they had a custom to be strict.
But why do we do today?
But רש"י, Rashi, no but let me just finish, but רש"י, Rashi,
but you're right that the phrase נהרא נהרא ופשטיה nahara nahara u'fastei
really means in the sense of greater הלכתי halachic pluralism, it doesn't
just mean just different customs, it means different practices, respecting different practices
within an area of הלכה. halacha. So what do we do today
about the chicken? Oh we're not done with the story. We're not
done with the whole discussion. We have a little while left in
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara is not done discussing the dislocated
thigh. Okay, so let's go back.
But it's very interesting because you're talking about טרפה treifa and כשירה,
k'sheira, not...
I understand, so you're right, it's practice, it's not custom.
So what one place held is completely טרפה, treifa, the other
place holds what's כשר kasher or what you're eating is. Right. Sure,
the משנה Mishna says we'll see later when we get to בשר
בחלב basar b'chalav discussions, that במקומו של רבי יוסי הגלילי היו אוכלים
עוף בחלב. bimkomo shel Rabbi Yossi HaGlili hayu ochlim of b'chalav. So
there was one place that they actually had, you know, chicken and
milk. So, all right, cooked together, not just eaten together. All right,
so let's take a look now. All right, so yes, so he's
saying this is true, but רב, Rav, he still held said that
this dislocated leg bone, thigh bone, was כשר. kasher. Now we're not
done. אתא רבי אבא אשכחיה לרבי ירמיה בר אבא. Ata Rabbi Abba
ashchecha l'Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba. So רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, a lot
of fathers and sons going on here.
רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba, presumably his son, דקבדק
בצומת הגידין d'kabadek b'tzomet hagidim
that was like the earlier story, checking not here about the dislocated
bone. Remember there are two problems with the rear bone of a
cow, one is dislocated and the other is this cluster of sinews.
So he was checking about the צומת הגידין tzomet hagidim of the
chicken to see if it was a problem. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so he said to him, למה ליה למר כולי האי, lama lei
l'mar kulei hai, why are you bothering to do this? Now, again,
the fact that he calls him מר, mar, the master, sounds like
this might not have been his son.
So I don't know exactly. But anyway, so why are you bothering
to check for the צומת הגידין tzomet hagidim by, you know, in
terms of by chickens? והא רב הונא אמר רב שמוטה בעוף כשירה,
v'ha Rav Huna amar Rav shumta b'of k'sheira, רב הונא Rav Huna
said in the name of רב, Rav, that a dislocated thigh of
a bird is kosher, which the argument being one of two. Either
therefore we'd see that the thigh, the legs of chickens are not
at all to be compared to the rear legs of cows and
we don't make any of those applications, so it's just, you know,
we don't treat them the same. Or it's saying, look, if the
bone can be dislocated and be kosher, then certainly lower down if
there's a problem with the sinews, that shouldn't be a problem if
even if it's completely dislocated. Now, not necessarily, dislocated it's still connected,
right, if there's a... so that might not be a good קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. But let's see what he says. But he says
look, if dislocated is kosher, this should be kosher too. So he
said, let's see what the answer was.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, אנא מתניתא ידענא.
ana matnita yadana. I don't know about this teaching in the name
of רב, Rav, I know our משנה. Mishna. What does our משנה
Mishna say? בהמה שנחתכו רגליה מן הארכובה ולמטה כשירה. behema shenichtechu ragleha
min ha'arkuva u'l'mata k'sheira. If the animal, if like a cow's leg
is cut from this lower leg joint and below, it's kosher. מן
הארכובה ולמעלה פסולה, min ha'arkuva u'l'ma'ala pesula,
from this lower knee joint and above it's פסולה. pesula. So that's
the actual cut, I had mentioned that, the bone is broken. וכן
שניטל צומת הגידין, v'chen shenital tzomet hagidim, and similarly if this collection
of sinews has been cut or removed. So you see it's true
by cows, and he's saying and I assume... What's true by cows
is true by birds. So we, this is the problem. He says
dislocated, Rav said dislocated hip thigh bone by a bird is kosher,
which means we don't say it's similar to cows. He says look,
as far as I know, it's a problem by cows, it's a
problem by birds. Okay, so אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so he said
back to him, את מפרש שמעתתיה... at mefaraish shemateteih... I'm sorry, I
skipped a line. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, אישתק, Ishtik, so he didn't
tell... I skipped a line again. Okay. ואמר רב אלא וכן בעוף.
V'amar Rav ala v'chen b'of. And now we're talking about Rav, I
have a tradition that Rav himself said the same problem by cows
applies to birds. Okay, so once again we've got a contradiction, an
implicit contradiction of Rav, not about the dislocated thigh bone but about
do we make this comparison. So we know that a, you know,
a severed צומת הגידים tzomet hagidim is a problem by cows, Rav
said the same thing by birds, and now you're telling me that
another tradition in the name of Rav says a dislocated thigh bone
is not a problem by birds. So what is it? Do we
compare birds or not compare birds to cows? So,
so אישתק, Ishtik, so he was silent, he didn't have a good
answer to how we have these contradictory statements of Rav. אמר ליה,
Amar Lei, so he said back to him,
this was רב ירמיה בר אבא Rav Yirmiya bar Abba said back
to רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. He said back to him, דילמא שאני
ליה בין שמוטה לחתוכה. dilma shani leih bein shmuta l'chatucha.
Maybe for Rav there's a difference between dislocated and severed. Meaning, okay,
we don't say one rule, compare birds to cows by the hind
leg, you know, it's either all or nothing, maybe it depends. So
when it comes to dislocated, we won't compare it, and therefore a
dislocated leg of a bird will be okay. When it comes to
severed, the severed צומת הגידים, tzomet hagidim, we will compare it. So
it's not an all or nothing. So אמר ליה, Amar Lei,
so he said now back, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said back to
רב ירמיה בר אבא, Rav Yirmiya bar Abba, ואת מפרש שמעתתא דרב?
v'at mefaraish shemateta d'Rav?
You're trying to explain Rav's teachings, you know, by your own logic?
בפירוש אמר רב, B'feirush amar Rav, Rav actually explicitly said exactly that
distinction: שמוטה כשירה חתוכה פסולה. shmuta k'sheira, chatucha psula.
That a dislocated thigh bone of a bird is kosher, but a
severed leg or צומת הגידים tzomet hagidim is פסול, pasul, is invalid.
ואל תתמה, V'al titmah, and do not be astounded. How can we
say that if it's dislocated higher up it's okay and severed lower
down it's not good? שהרי חתוכה מכאן ומתה, חתוכה מכאן וחיה. Sheharei
chatucha mikan u'metah, chatucha mikan v'chayah.
You can cut an animal in one place and it will live,
cut another place and it will die, and therefore you cannot make
קל וחומר kal v'chomer types of comparison. Now again, what's fascinating is
if רב ירמיה בר אבא Rav Yirmiya bar Abba said
back... I'm sorry, if רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said back, you know,
don't just explain Rav based on your סברא, sevara, Rav actually explicitly
made this distinction, so why was he silent in the initial exchange?
Maybe, you know, maybe it took him a moment to get his
wits and then to remember that Rav had made this distinction. But
here you have this question, right? On the one hand, the משנה
Mishnah says that if a chicken's legs are broken, it's okay. And
on the other hand, we actually know that broken hind legs of
a cow, you know, certainly anywhere above the lower ankle, are going
to be no good. So do you make these comparisons or not
make these comparisons with cows? And we're looking here that at one
stage the גמרא Gemara says everything is compared, and if that's true,
the only place a broken bone by a chicken would be allowed
would be at the very bottom of the leg, which didn't sound
that way from the משנה. Mishnah. But here we're trying to split
our vote according to Rav and we're trying to say that a
broken leg or a severed צומת הגידים tzomet hagidim we would learn
out, and again, severely limit the statement in our משנה Mishnah that
it's not a problem, that we would learn out from בהמה. behemah.
But dislocated, that we're actually not going to learn out from בהמה
behemah and that we're going to say is not a problem by
birds. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is going to say this whole
thing over again in case you didn't get it the first time.
So let's take a look.
כי סליק רבי אבא, Ki salik Rabbi Abba, when רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba went up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה לרבי זירא, ashkechei
l'Rabbi Zeira, he found רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira דיתיב וקאמר. d'yativ v'ka'amar.
He found רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira that was sitting in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and saying over the following
teaching: אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna amar Rav, שמוטת
הירך בעוף טריפה, shmutat hayerech b'of tereifa, that a dislocated thigh in
the bird is a טריפה. tereifa. Now we had רב הונא Rav
Huna saying in the name of Rav that it was כשירה. k'sheira.
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so he said back to him, רבי אבא...
Rabbi Abba... okay, again, it's the same רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, he's
now on his way back to... now he's after having this whole
exchange, he went up to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So he said
to him, חיי דמר, chayei d'mar, by the life of the master,
מיומא דסליק מר להכא, m'yoma d'salik mar l'hacha, from the day you,
talking to רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, went up here to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, so you left us in בבל, Bavel, you made עליה.
aliyah. Since you have left us, let me tell you what's happened
back in בבל. Bavel. הוי לן פיתחא פומא hevei lan pitcha puma
קמיה דרב הונא. kamie d'Rav Huna. It's a very interesting phrase. We
had an opportunity to open our mouths in front of רב הונא,
Rav Huna, meaning to inquire about this question. So could just mean
like we hadn't had a chance to ask him yet, but it
also sounds like, you know, you had to actually, you know, weigh
your opportunities, like you wouldn't always, he wouldn't always have tolerated just
random questions. But anyway, we had the opportunity to ask רב הונא
Rav Huna the following issue: ושאילנה, v'shailneih, and we asked him. about
this thing, about the dislocated thigh of a bird. ואמר לן ve'amar
lan and he said to us שמוטת ירך בעוף כשרה shmutat yerech
ba'of kesheira that it's כשר. kosher. Here you are teaching in the
name of רב Rav that it's טריפה. treifa. We actually asked רב
הונא Rav Huna and he said it was כשר. kosher. Now and
this was רב הונא, Rav Huna, it's a tradition of what רב
הונא Rav Huna said in the name of רב. Rav. So we
heard straight from him that it was כשר, kosher, again notice this
theme of traditions, right? Did רב הונא Rav Huna say כשר, kosher,
did רב הונא Rav Huna say טריפה, treifa, did רב, Rav, right
there were different versions of רב, Rav, what did רב Rav say?
Okay. ואשכחניה נמי לרבי ירמיה בר אבא, vashkechneih nami leRabbi Yirmiyah bar
Abba, we found רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, דיתיב
וקא בדיק בצומת הגידין, deyativ veka badik bitzomat hagidin, he was checking
the צומת הגידין. Tzomet HaGidin. ואקשי ליה vakshi leih
and we asked him, לא סבר ליה מר הא דאמר רב הונא
אמר רב שמוטת ירך בעוף כשרה? lo savar leih mar ha de'amar
Rav Huna amar Rav shmutat yerech ba'of kesheira? Now we're going to
the whole revisiting the whole story because this is the רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba that was part of that story and now he's telling
over the story to רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. So I asked him,
don't you know that רב Rav says a dislocated thigh bone is
כשר? kosher? So why are you checking the צומת הגידין? Tzomet HaGidin?
אמר ליה, amar leih, he said, אנא מתניתין ידענא, ana matnitin yadana,
I know our משנה, Mishnah, בהמה שנחתכו רגליה מן הארכובה ולמטה כשרה,
beheima shenichtechu ragleha min ha'arkuva ulemata kesheira, מן הארכובה ולמעלה פסולה, min
ha'arkuva ulemala pesula, an animal that has a severed knee bone and
above it's a problem, וכן שניטלה צומת הגידין, vechen shenitla tzomat hagidin,
and similarly if the collection of sinews has been removed. So we
know that's true about animals. ואמר רב עלן, ve'amar Rav alan, I
have a tradition again of רב, Rav, וכן בעוף, vechen ba'of, it
says it's the same by birds. So I have a tradition of
רב Rav that this is a problem by birds. ואמרי ליה, vamri
leih,
so then I, said רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, said to him, אי
הכי קשיא דרב אדרב, ee hachi kashya deRav a deRav, so but
now רב Rav is contradicting himself. Is a dislocated thigh okay? A
severed צומת הגידין Tzomet HaGidin is no good. That's what I said
to him. ואישתיק, ve'ishtik, he was silent. ואקשי ליה, vakshi leih, and
then I, so now it's a little clear actually who's speaking to
whom, it wasn't so clear from the עמוד א. Amud Aleph. And
I asked him, ודילמא שאני ליה לרב בין שמוטה לחתוכה, vedilma shani
leih leRav bein shmuta lachatucha, that maybe רב Rav distinguishes between severed
and dislocated. ואמר לי, ve'amar li, and he said back to me,
ואת מפרש שמעתיה דרב, ve'at mefareish shmateih deRav, you
are like speculating on what רב Rav says? בפירוש אמר רב, befeirosh
amar Rav, רב Rav explicitly said, שמוטה כשרה חתוכה פסולה, shmuta kesheira
chatucha pesula, dislocated is okay, severed is no good. So that was
a complete recap, quite fascinating though רבי אבא Rabbi Abba who was
a primary party to it went up to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and he repeated the whole story. The upshot of it is I
will accept that צומת הגידין Tzomet HaGidin is a problem, but now
we have a pretty clear tradition in בבל Bavel that רב Rav
said that dislocated is okay. We asked רב הונא, Rav Huna, he
said that, this whole story with רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba, everybody affirmed or accepted that רב Rav said that dislocated
was okay even if severed צומת הגידין Tzomet HaGidin is no good.
And again notice this theme of different traditions over who actually said
what. Not just debates, but actually different traditions about what רב הונא
Rav Huna said, different traditions about what רב Rav said and so
on. Anyway so that's what he reported to רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira.
For us it became clear in בבל Bavel that רב Rav said
that dislocated is okay.
ואת מה בידך, ve'at mah beyadecha, you now רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira,
you've been here in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, what traditions have you
learned regarding this dislocated
thigh? Because I told you now what רב Rav says, what have
you learned? So ואת מה בידך, ve'at mah beyadecha, so הכי אמר
רב
חייא בר אשי אמר רב, hachi amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi amar
Rav, so here's what רב חייא בר אשי Rav Chiya bar Ashi
says in the name of רב. Rav. Again a tradition in the
name of רב. Rav. שמוטת ירך בעוף טריפה. shmutat yerech ba'of treifa.
So maybe I'll accept that רב הונא Rav Huna and other people
in בבל Bavel accepted that רב Rav said that it was כשר,
kosher, but I have traditions still in the name of רב Rav
that it's a טריפה. treifa. That it's טריפה. treifa. וכן אמר רבי
יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי יוחנן, vechen amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi
amar Rabbi Yochanan, and now forget רב, Rav, a tradition in the
name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. שמוטת ירך בעוף טריפה, shmutat yerech
ba'of treifa, that a dislocated thigh is a טריפה. treifa. ואמר רבי
יעקב בר אידי, ve'amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, and רבי יעקב בר
אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi said, אלמלא הוי רבי יוחנן באתריה דחורי
בה חברותא להתירו, ilmalei havei Rabbi Yochanan be'atreih dechorei bah chavruta lehatiro,
if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had been in the place where his
colleagues ruled to make it מותר, muttar, לא פרחי, lo parchi, he
would not have like thrashed, again this word of thrashing is the
word by animals. Now what does that mean he wouldn't have thrashed?
What it means that he like wouldn't have resisted, that's what it
sounds like. It sounds like if he had been where the other
authorities פסקנ'ד paskin'd it was מותר, muttar, these other authorities who פסקנ'ד
paskin'd it was מותר muttar were of such greater stature that he
would not have opposed them.
דאמר רבי חנינא אמר רב, de'amar Rabbi Chanina amar Rav, because again
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says in the name of
רב... Rav... no, Rabbi. דאמר רבי חנינא אמר רבי, de'amar Rabbi Chanina
amar Rebbi, שמוטת ירך בעוף כשרה. shmutat yerech ba'of kesheira.
So now we have a tradition that goes back to the Tannaic
period. Until now we've been debating רב Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan at the Amoraic level. But we have a tradition that goes
back to רבי Rebbi that says a dislocated thigh is כשר. kosher.
תרנגולת הויא ליה לרבי חנינא, tarnigolet havya leih leRabbi Chanina,
and there's a story, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina had a chicken, שנשמטה
ירך שלה, shenishmeta yerech shela,
that its thigh was dislocated. And he brought it before רבי, Rebbi,
and והתירה לו, v'hitira lo, and רבי Rebbi said it's permissible. ומלחה
רבי חנינא, u'malacha Rebbi Chanina, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina preserved it in
salt, והוה מורי בה הלכה לתלמידיו, v'hava mori bah halacha l'talmidav,
and he used it as a visual aid to teach his students,
and he said זה התיר לי רבי, זה התיר לי רבי, zeh
hitir li Rebbi, zeh hitir li Rebbi, and he would like take
out his chicken and say, this was the chicken that רבי Rebbi
said was permissible. You see, this had a dislocated thigh and רבי
Rebbi said it was permissible. So now you have a whole debate
what רב Rav said, but obviously the גמרא Gemara seems to be
very much leaning to the tradition that רב Rav said dislocated thigh
was okay. You had some positions, traditions in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
one in the name of רב Rav as well, that says it's
no good. But now it's like, oh, if they heard that רבי
Rebbi said it, or they'd been there when רבי Rebbi פסקן paskened
it, nobody would have ever disagreed with it. And we have this
whole fascinating little story, so you're expecting the גמרא's Gemara going to
end up that it's okay. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara ends
up. לית הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא, Leis hilchasa k'chol hani shmaatsa, we
don't rule like this whole previous discussion, כי
הא דשאיל רבי יוסי בן נהוראי את רבי יהושע בן לוי. ki
ha d'shail Rabbi Yossi ben Nehorai es Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. So
רבי יוסי בן נהוראי Rabbi Yossi ben Nehorai asked רבי יהושע בן
לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, קדרה כמה בכמה, kideira kama b'kama, to
sort of digress a second but then we'll circle back, how big
of a hole in the trachea is a problem? You remember like
a hole the size of a coin is a problem. So he
asked him this question, אמר לו משנה שלמה שנינו, amar lo mishna
shleima shaninu, it's an explicit משנה, mishna, עד איסר איטלקי, ad issar
italki, a hole up to the size of this Italian איסר issar
is okay, less than that is no good.
אמר לו, Amar lo, ורחל אחת היתה בשכונתנו, v'rachel achas haysa b'shchunateinu,
didn't we have a young sheep in our
village, שנקדר הקנה שלה, she'nikdar hakana shela, that there was a hole
in its trachea, ועשו לה קרומית של קנה, v'asu lah krumis shel
kneh, and they made for it basically some type of a like
splint, or not splint, whatever, some type of a thing out of
reeds to stop up the hole, or not stop it up but
to cover it up, bandage up the hole, right? וחיתה, v'chayesa, and
it survived, so how can you say that with a big hole
it's a טריפה? treifa? We actually don't, now you could say an
animal's a טריפה treifa unless you do some type of an intervention,
but if you remember when the גמרא Gemara before asked about the
hunters that when they hit an animal in certain place it dies,
so why don't we have this to the list, the גמרא Gemara
says no, no, because if you were to apply some type of
medicine it would live, which makes it clear from the גמרא's Gemara
perspective that if an animal's a טריפה, treifa, even with intervention it
can't live. So here he's saying to him, how can you say
with a hole in the trachea it'll die? It's a טריפה. treifa.
We actually did this medical intervention and it lived, and if something's
a טריפה treifa it shouldn't live even with intervention.
אמר לו, Amar lo, so he said back to him, ועל דא
סמכת, v'al da samacht, this is what you're relying on? והלא הלכה
רווחת בישראל, v'halo halacha ravacha b'Yisrael, I'll give you another case where
you know where something like this could be raised but it's sort
of dismissed.
There's a widespread הלכה halacha among in ישראל, Yisrael, שמוטת ירך בעוף
טריפה. shmutas yareich b'of treifa.
This is why we're bringing in the story, that a dislocated thigh
by a bird is a
טריפה. treifa. ותרנגולת היתה לו לרבי שמעון בן חלפתא, V'tarnegoles haysa lo
l'Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta, and I can tell you a story, רבי
שמעון בן חלפתא Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta had a chicken, שנשמטה ירך
שלה, she'nishmeta yareich shela, that its thigh was dislocated, ועשו לה שפופרת
של קנה, v'asu lah shfoferes shel kneh, and he made basically a
splint out of some reed, וחיתה, v'chayesa, and it survived. So, and
nevertheless we still rule that that type of an animal's a טריפה.
treifa. Okay, what's the answer though? אלא מאי אית לך למימר, Ela
mai is lach l'meimar, how do you deal with this contrary evidence?
תוך שנים עשר חודש הוי, toch shneim asar chodesh havei, it was
within twelve months that it survived, it didn't die immediately. Notice by
the way when we said a טריפה treifa dies, we never said
in what time frame. Okay, the גמרא Gemara once or twice before
mentioned the twelve months, and here is where the גמרא's Gemara really
going to focus on it. This is the time where we're finally
introducing the idea that die does not mean die immediately, it means
die within a year. So we'll have to assume it died within
the year. So the fact that it survived doesn't prove because it
died within the year. הכא נמי תוך שנים עשר חודש הוי, hacha
nami toch shneim asar chodesh havei, here too with the hole in
the trachea, the fact that it survived, that was within the year.
Okay, and so let's just pause here for a second. So basically
what we see is after all of this evidence, you know, רבי
Rebbi ruled and you know whoever it was, you know, actually preserved
the chicken and demonstrated all this thing, the גמרא Gemara nevertheless rejects
it. We've had that before, that the sort of theoretical discussion is
heading in one way and at the end the גמרא Gemara says
but the real הלכה halacha is the opposite. Now the question is
why, how does it arrive at that conclusion? It never actually tells
us, but the sense one gets often when you have that like
after a discussion it says הלכתא, hilchasa, is that it more has
to do with just the what has become the accepted practice. And
that particularly is underscored here by the phrase of הלכה רווחת בישראל.
halacha ravacha b'Yisrael. The fact that it says בישראל b'Yisrael sounds like
it's not just rabbis who are ruling this, but the widespread you
know practice has been become this thing. Now how does the practice
become that? Do people do things without asking שאלות? shailos? Do certain
rabbis start פסקן paskening that way לחומרא l'chumra to play it safe
or because they're not able to you know whatever? How exactly you
know that plays out is not always easy to determine, but we
should acknowledge, and I think this is sometimes a major problem in
how הלכה halacha is often dealt with nowadays, you know, that... that
that is a major factor in הלכה, halacha, both לקולא l'kula and
לחומרא. l'chumra. You know, so sometimes, you know, certain on the books
certain things seem like they should be totally permissible and then the
accepted practice has become to be much stricter, but sometimes also it's
the reverse. You know, the books might lead to a stricter conclusion
and the practice has been more lenient and that's certainly, you know,
the whole תוספות Tosfos dealing with the practices in אשכנז Ashkenaz which
differed from the גמרא Gemara and how to reconcile them. You know,
or פוסקים poskim like the ערוך השולחן Aruch HaShulchan who was the
rabbi of a community who was much more responsive to what is
the common, what is the practice. A: what the people need, but
besides what people need, also what the accepted practice is and weighed
that very heavily, you know, against, against, you know, what might have
been the simple simple meaning of what was on the books. So
that type of a tension between what's practiced and what's sort of
on the books plays out a lot in הלכה halacha and that
has to do also with this shift of 'forget all the discussion,
here's the widespread practice'. Yes.
Well, there are practices that have been adopted almost universally like Ashkenazic
Jews not eating קטניות. kitniyos.
Right, right, those are מנהגים. minhagim. Right, right, הלל ראש חודש,
Hallel
Rosh
Chodesh, הלל ראש חודש Hallel Rosh Chodesh is more a halachic... well,
whatever. Okay, but anyway, yes, that's more מנהגים. minhagim. We're talking here
more about practices within a realm of
הלכה halacha so
you go this way or you go that way, right, not a
new custom, and how much the practice, whether לקולא l'kula or לחומרא,
l'chumra, plays against what the sort of, you know, theoretical and book
analysis might lead to. Now the other important point, and this is
now what we're going to focus on, gets us back to that
great question about science and הלכה, halacha, because here somebody actually tried
to do an empirical test, or maybe they weren't trying to disprove
הלכה halacha but they just tried to, you know, to save their
kicker. But anyway, but it was brought as evidence against and the
response of the גמרא Gemara was, was that it must have died
within a year. So first of all we're introducing the idea that
it doesn't die right away, which we'll discuss later. Okay, that's important
as a general definition. We're also have implicitly assumed that no animal
can be an exception. Why didn't he just say, 'Okay, sometimes there's
an exception'? He didn't say that. We've also assumed that medical intervention
does not matter. Okay, now that is going to lead to real
problems in the time of the ראשונים Rishonim because if, because if
I now am able to show you an animal that survived twelve
months with or without, even with medical intervention and certainly without, so
what's your response to me going to be? You can't say, 'Oh,
well, it's not true by one hundred percent of the animals, only
true by ninety-nine percent of the animals.' If that was true why
didn't he just give that answer, you know, 'It's there are some
exceptions'? No, it sounds like it's supposed to be one hundred percent
true. So if the only answer is it died after a year,
what do you do if I give you evidence that it didn't
die after a year, that it survived the year? And these were
the questions that the ראשונים Rishonim were challenged with and led to
this whole issue about what happens when empirical evidence contradicts, you know,
the הלכה. halacha. And actually the גמרא Gemara is now going to
have a story just like that. What do you want to say,
Josh?
Well, the fact that it dies after a year and then how
long does a chicken live anyway, so many things in a year
that killed it, but isn't, am I not entitled to say, you
know what, שמעון בן חלפתא Shimon ben Chalafta ate a chicken that
was with this broken... that was good enough for him, it's good
enough for me? Following שמעון בן חלפתא? Shimon ben Chalafta?
I understand, but why don't you say that about so many things
in the גמרא? Gemara? And if יוסי הגלילי Yose HaGlili ate עוף
בחלב, of b'chalav, so I'm gonna eat עוף בחלב. of b'chalav.
But he knew that there was a problem, he knew that it
was a מחלוקת, machlokes, right?
No, actually it doesn't even say that he ate it, it just
says that it survived.
So why did he keep it?
Maybe he wanted it to lay eggs, you know?
I don't know.
But the point is that you can't just take any opinion. The
whole idea of the גמרא Gemara is that sometimes, you know, there's
a process of הלכה, halacha, some get confirmed and some get, you
know, marginalized and rejected and so...
But he was a big guy.
I know, but they're often... יוסי הגלילי Yose HaGlili was also a
big guy, so let's start having what's that, what's that chicken and
a milk dish, that's got to be a lot of that. Chicken
parmesan. Chicken parmesan, right. If it was good enough for יוסי הגלילי,
Yose HaGlili, it's good enough for me. All right, so let's take
a look. Now talking about שמעון בן חלפתא, Shimon ben Chalafta, that's
exactly this interesting story about empirical evidence used to test out הלכה.
halacha. Let's take a look. אמרו עליו על רבי שמעון בן חלפתא,
Amru alav al Rabi Shimon ben Chalafta, they said about רבי שמעון
בן חלפתא Rabi Shimon ben Chalafta שעסקן בדברים היה, she'askan bidvarim haya,
he was very involved in things, which I think the probably meaning
here is that he wanted to test things out, he really looked
at, he was he looked at empirical evidence. Okay, so let's take
a look. ועשה דבר להוציא מלבו של רבי יהודה, V'asa davar l'hotzi
milibo she'Rabi Yehuda, and he did something to disprove the position of
רבי יהודה. Rabi Yehuda. of רב יהודה. Reb Yehuda. What's רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda's position? שהיה רב יהודה אומר Sheaye Reb Yehuda omeir רב
יהודה Reb Yehuda said, this is in our
משנה, Mishnah, ניטלה הנוצה פסולה. nitla hanotzah pesula. If a bird is
lost its down, it's invalid, it's a טריפה. treifa. So he said,
I'm going to prove that you are wrong. ותרנגולת היתה לו לרבי
שמעון בן חלפתא, Vatarnigoles hayesa lo leReb Shimon bar Chalafta, he had
a chicken. So now it sounds like he was really doing these
things with his chickens to prove things about טריפות. treifos. Okay, he
had a experiment, he had a chicken שניטלה נוצה שלה, shenitla hanotzah
shelah, that it had its down removed. One wonders maybe he removed
the down to do the test, but okay, it lost its down.
והניחה בתנור, vehinnichah batanur, so he made sure it was going to
keep warm. He kept it near the oven or literally in the
oven. והניחה בתנור. vehinnichah batanur. וטלה לה במטלית של טרסיים. utelalah bamatlis
shel torsiyim. He covered it up with an apron of smelters, of
like you know, of iron workers, which is you know keeps something,
first of all will prevent it from burning I guess, but also
keeps it very warm. It's a very sort of thick and heavy
type of an apron. וגידלה כנפיים אחרונים יותר מן הראשונים. vegidlah knafayim
acharonim yoseir min harishonim. And then it grew new feathers which were
even better than the feathers that it had lost. So and it
survived, so he proved that רב יהודה Reb Yehuda was wrong. It's
not a טריפה. treifa. And again, even even though it's with intervention,
if something is a טריפה, treifa, it should die even with intervention.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says: ודילמא קסבר רב יהודה טריפה
משבחת? Vedilma kasavar Reb Yehuda treifa meshabbachas? Maybe רב יהודה Reb Yehuda
holds that even if an animal becomes a טריפה, treifa, it can
improve. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, one minute. So, I lost
my line. אם כן במידי דמטרפה בה? Im kein bimidi dimitrefah bah?
So, וגידלה כנפיים אחרונים יותר מן הראשונים. vegidlah knafayim acharonim yoseir min
harishonim. Even if a טריפה treifa can improve in other areas of
its body and can even maybe overcompensate for its loss, nobody would
say that a טריפה treifa restores
the thing that was injured better than it had originally been damaged.
And here we say that the wings were restored, the second wings
were better than the first. So now to say טריפה משבחת treifa
meshabbachas by the way, might be that you say טריפה חיה. treifa
chayah. Right, remember there is that opinion that even a טריפה treifa
can live. But his point seems to be: forget about חיה או
אינה חיה. chayah o eina chayah. If the animal can actually recover
and even better than it was, then on what basis can you
call it a טריפה treifa altogether? So so that was the argument.
Maybe if טריפה treifa other parts of the body will compensate, but
this thing itself, if it will recover, how do you call it
a טריפה? treifa? So here he actually used empirical evidence to rule
against רב יהודה. Reb Yehuda. Now so far it's not impossible because
I mean it's not a problem because he's ruling against רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda in favor of the חכמים. Chachamim. That the חכמים Chachamim
said that without feathers it's kosher and presumably he's just supporting the
position of the חכמים. Chachamim. But let's take to let's take a
look now at the next story. We're not done.
Feathers or down?
So that's the thing. He said רב יהודה Reb Yehuda said if
it's missing the down it's a טריפה. treifa. When it said that
it got better, it used the word feathers, but presumably in the
context you have to assume that that means down. But you're right,
that's the it's the problem was the walk of the down, so
presumably what happened was that it regrew the down. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says: Okay. מאי עסקן בדברים? Mai askein bidvarim? What
does this mean that he was like you know involved in things,
tested things out other than this one story? Presumably it means that
there's other cases he did this. So אמר משרשיא דכתיב: Amar Mesharshiya
dichsiv: so he because there was a verse. The verse in משלי
Mishlei says: לך אל נמלה עצל. Leich el nemala atzel.
Lazy one, go look at the ant. Right? The whole ant what
is it, the ant and the grasshopper? Right. So lazy one, go
look at the ant. ראה דרכיה. Re'ei deracheiha. See its ways. וחכם
vechocham and become wise. אשר אין לה קצין שוטר ומושל. Asher ein
lah katzin soteir umosheil. It has no sort of you know officer
or king or ruler. תכין בקיץ לחמה. Tachin bakayitz lachmah. It prepares
its you know its food in the in the summer. It works
in the summer even though nobody is telling it what to do.
So that's a little משל mashal in in משלי. Mishlei. Okay. So
he said: let's test that out. אמר איזל אחזי אי ודאי הוא
דלית לה מלכא. Amar eizel achzei i vadai hu delais lah malka.
Let me see if it's really true if ants don't have kings.
Okay. So אזל בתקופת תמוז. azal bitkufas Tammuz. He went in the
period of תמוז Tammuz in the
summertime. פרסיה לגלימיה אקינא דשומשמני. parcei liglimei akina dishumshumani. He spread his
cloak over an anthill to make it shady. Okay. It was a
sunny day but he spread his cloak there that it would be
shady. נפיק אתא חד מינייהו. nafik asa chad minaihu. So one ant,
a scout ant came out. Do ants have scout ants? Okay I
don't know, a scout ant came
out. אסנח ביה סימנא. isnech bei simana. So he tagged the ant
that came out, like scientists right they'll tag an animal to see
what happens to it, so he like put a סימן siman on
it, like made a little red marker or something. על אמר להו.
al amar lehu. So the ant went into the anthill and said
to the fellow ants, presumably, I mean we don't
we don't speak ant, but presumably based on what happened we can
infer that it went back and communicated to its fellow ants that
נפל טולא. nefalti tulla. Hey, it's shady outside, it's safe to go
out. נפקו ואתו. nafku va'asu. So then all of
the ants
דליה לגלימיה, Dalyah l'glimei, he now so now that all the ants
were out he removed his cloak, okay, נפשה שמשא, nafsha shimsha, so
the sun beat down on them, so they so all the ants
were upset at the scout. So what did they do? נפלו ליה
וקטלוה, Nafalu lei v'katlei, they all got ganged up and killed the
scout ant. So אמר, amar, so he said, שמע מינה לית להו
מלכא, Sh'ma mina, leis lehu malka, I see that ants have no
king, nobody is instilling a rule of law, right? They just went
ahead and they killed this ant. There was nobody that, you know,
there was no proceeding. No law? Exactly. די אית להו, Dee islahu,
because if they had a king, הרמנא דמלכא לבעו, harman d'malka l'va'u,
they would certainly need permission from the king, they wouldn't just immediately
kill the guy. So אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי,
amar lei Rav Acha brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi, so Rav Acha the
son of Rava now this presumably, you'll notice all of this was
in Aramaic. It was said by, you know, this רב משרשיא, Rav
Mesharshya, it was not, you know, so it does not sound, it
sounds it's questionable whether, I mean this, I don't know that they
were speculating, they had a tradition that this was רב שמעון בן
חלפתא, Rav Shimon ben Chalafta, but it's certainly different than the previous
story which was a very straight, you know, test, experiment about a
הלכה halakha of טריפות, treifos, right? This is a little more fantastical.
Okay, anyway, so רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha brei d'Rava said
to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, she said where were we? He said
to him, ודילמא, v'dilma, what type of a proof was that? ודילמא
מלכא הוה בהדייהו, V'dilma malka hava behadayhu, maybe the king was one
of the lynch mob? So they implicitly had the king's permission because
he was one of the people that were going after the scout
ant. Number one. אי נמי הרמנא דמלכא הוה נקיטא, Inami, harman d'malka
hava nekita, maybe they already had a ruling from the king. If
any ant ever causes trouble you have the permission to go and
kill him. Okay, אי נמי, Inami, or בין מלכא למלכא הוה, bein
malka l'malka hava, maybe it was in between kings, maybe they were
in a period where they didn't have a king.
Do you see the metaphor for rabbinic authority?
What do you mean?
That, you know, the ants are functioning, each one does what it's
supposed to do, right? They have no one authority telling them what
to do. They're arguing over the difference in whether the chicken is
כשר kosher or טריפה treif and everyone has their own opinion. Uh-huh.
And they're
just trying to bring their tribe well let's take a
look, well let's take a look at the next slide and think
about that. דכתיב, D'chtiv, and here I will show you a verse
that shows about how what it means how there could be periods
without authority. Right. Exactly. בימים ההם אין מלך בישראל איש הישר בעיניו
יעשה. Bayamim hahem ein melech b'Yisrael, ish hayashar b'einav ya'aseh. So look,
when there are no king there could be a system of kings,
there could be rulers, but in a period between the rulers it's
the anarchy. So maybe that's what was going on with the ants.
So let's finish the story and then I'll go back to your
point. אלא, Ela, so rather, here's the response to to רב שמעון
בן חלפתא, Rav Shimon ben Chalafta, סמוך אהימנותא
דשלמה. S'moch a-heimnusa d'Shlomo. Just trust שלמה המלך, Shlomo HaMelech, don't go
ahead and do your experiment. Okay, now I want to say that
that actually is before we get to your משל mashal interpretation I'm
looking at this through the lens of this whole question about sort
of science, empirical evidence against, you know, against הלכה, halakha, so here
the basic response is, you know, trust authority, right? Trust Shlomo, trust
the Rabbis, trust הלכה, halakha, don't go ahead and need to do
all of this experiment and empirical studies. So the fact that he
was labeled as עסקן בדברים, askan bidvarim, which one gets a feeling
is not a compliment, right? You know, so it's like, okay, you
feel you need to go try everything out empirically, you know, you
should just trust the authorities, which really speaks to a pre-empirical time
where knowledge came from authorities and not from, you know, direct empirical
observation. So the question here is, so reading it that way, it's
like we don't, you know, we're not interested in him, we're already
predisposed to rejecting what he's going ahead to say, which is pretty
much how the field of טריפות treifos played out for the next
2,000 years exactly like that, predisposed to reject any external evidence. The
question is in one place here though it says that he disproved
רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, that seems like it might be relevant like
will we take his position to try to reject רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda and support the חכמים Chachamim that disagree? So there's a little
תוספות Tosfos on this, I just want to show you. So he
says, איזיל ואחזי היכי הוה מילתא, eeza v'echzi heichi hava milsa, let
me go see, let me go test out, you know, this story
about the ants that's on the גמרא. Gemara. So he says, ואף
על גב דחטיף האי גוונא במסכת תענית מלגלג גבי ההוא תלמיד דאמר
ליה רבי יוחנן אם לא ראית לא האמנת מלגלג על דברי חכמים
אתה. v'af al gav d'chatif hagavna b'masechet Taanit m'lagleg gabei hahu talmid
d'amar lei Rebbe Yochanan im lo ra'isa lo he'emanta, m'lagleg al divrei
Chachamim ata. So there was a story again, but this was something
fantastical, that like רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan was saying like in the
messianic times the trees are going to have fruit the size of
like watermelons or I forget what exactly it was. So it said
that a certain student was saying. Ha, that's
impossible. And then he went and he saw something something similar to
it which showed him that these types of things were possible. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said back to him you are a derider,
a mocker of the words of sages. Why do you need to
see it? You should just believe even if you don't see it.
So here was somebody that actually
was taken to task for questioning and for not believing until he
could test it out. So here too why is ר' שמעון בן
חלפתא Rebbe Shimon ben Chalafta getting the light touch if this is
a problem? Well let's read תוספות Tosfos' answer and then I'll take
your question. So he says, שאני הכא שבא לברר
ולהודיע איך ידע שלמה. Shani hacha sheba levarer ulehodia eich yada Shlomo.
So תוספות Tosfos' is reading it is he wasn't trying to disprove
the Rabbis he was trying, or שלמה, Shlomo, he was trying to
prove them. He wasn't skeptical; he says okay, I accept it, let
me just confirm it. So as opposed to being skeptical and rejecting
it and having an axe to grind to prove that it was
wrong, he was trying to prove that it was right. But even
so, the גמרא Gemara's response to him is why do you need
to prove it's right by empirical evidence? Just trust
authority. Even if you're trying to prove them to confirm them, who
needs to go ahead and do experiments? A fascinating גמרא Gemara about
the whole issue of authority as opposed to observation. Yes Charlie.
But I've had cats since I was a kid and they don't
have venom in their legs.
So that is exactly what happens.
The ראשונים Rishonim are challenged by this. They'll say I'm not trying
to do an experiment, I just see my cow that has this
problem and it's been around for a year and it survived. So
that leaves the problem because A, you can't say medical intervention makes
a difference, you can't say it's an exception, those were rejected here.
And what you wind up doing is you want your observation to
weigh—not even here was maybe to confirm and even there we said
don't bother—and you want it to contradict tradition. So that led to
a whole effort in the ראשונים Rishonim to try to find ways
to reject the
evidence. And this גמרא Gemara really already predicts that. Okay so in
terms of what you wanted to say רבקה, Rivka, what did you
want to say? That this is, if anything, I think this is
speaking about the need for authority, right? Because if there's no authority
then they'll just have lynch mobs. And when there's no authority everybody
does whatever they want, איש הישר בעיניו יעשה. ish hayashar be'einav ya'aseh.
They functioned very well until he messed with them.
Oh I see. A normal
ant, right, that's שלמה Shlomo's point; ants do everything they're supposed to
do.
Right, but without his interference.
Right, that's interesting.
And שלמה Shlomo didn't talk about a king, שלמה Shlomo said learn
from the ant.
Yeah but he said the ant, no he does say the ant
does his work without any king telling him what to do.
Right, so he's and this is in the
context of a הלכה.
halacha. So there's an agreement here
where he's saying the Rabbis are wrong.
Right, okay, that's interesting. Interesting. Okay, let's just read one more line.
I think we're done. Let me just see
here. Okay, and then we'll have to end here. So we will
pick up tomorrow with going back to this הלכה halakhic question of
how long an animal has to survive or do we expect an
animal will die. We've introduced now a timeframe; it doesn't die right
away, it dies within the year. We're going to look at that
question of what is the timeframe starting tomorrow. Okay.